Finding Aid for Wendell E. Hulcher papers, 1959-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wendell E. Hulcher papers 1959-1971
Hulcher, Wendell E. (Wendell Ellsworth), 1922-1999.
1 oversize folder
35 linear feet
851517 Aa 2; UAm
Ann Arbor, Michigan, Republican city councilman, 1960-1964; mayor, 1965-1969, and deputy director of the U.S. Office of Intergovernmental Relations; councilman and mayoralty files; also materials concerning his activities with several U.S. government agencies and Florida Southern College.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Wendell E. Hulcher (donor no. 4726 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Wendell E. Hulcher was Republican mayor of Ann Arbor, Michigan serving from 1965 to 1969. He had previously served as a city councilman, 1960-1964. After leaving office in 1969, Hulcher served as deputy director in the US Office of Intergovernmental Relations, 1969 to 1971, and as a staff member of the American Revolution Bicentennial Commission. From 1979 until his retirement in 1993, Hulcher was a professor of business and economics at Florida Southern College. Wendell Hulcher died in 1999.
The Hulcher collection consists primarily of files created while serving as city councilman, 1960-1964, and as mayor of Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1965-1969. Some of the topics confronting city government at that time included the Fair Housing Ordinance and the work of the Human Relations Commission, revision of the zoning ordinance and the sign ordinance, Police-Community Relations, and relation with the University of Michigan.
Subjects:
Agnew, Spiro T., 1918-1996.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Mayors--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; City planning--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Florida Southern College.; Housing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Hulcher, Wendell Elsworth, 1922-; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Municipal government--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Republican Party (Mich.); United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Mayors.; Automobiles.; Hulcher, Wendell Elsworth, 1922-; Mayors--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Politics and government--1961-1970.; Rites and ceremonies.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Mayoralty files
  - Topical File 1965-1969
    - Accomplishments 1965 (Box 1)
    - Administrator (Box 1)
    - Airport (Box 1)
    - All America Cities Award (Box 1)
    - American Legion (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Area Foundation (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Art Association (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Citizens Council (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Citizens Safety and Traffic Council (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor City Employees (A.F.S.C.M.E. Local 369) (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Civic Housing Development Corporation (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Civic Theatre (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Garden Club (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Historical Commission (Convention of Assent) (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Independent Housing, Inc. (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Junior Chamber of Commerce (Jaycees) (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Public Library (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor School Board (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Township Citizens' Development Council (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti Urban Area. Policy Committee (Box 1)
    - Annual Reports (Box 1)
    - Assessor (Box 1)
    - Atlanta Trip (Martin Luther King funeral) (Box 1)
    - Atomic Energy Commission (Box 1)
    - Attorney (Box 1)
    - Belize, British Honduras (Sister City) (Box 1)
    - Biographical Data (Box 1)
    - Blue Ribbon Committee on Finance (Box 1)
    - Board of Realtors (Box 2)
    - Board of Supervisors (Box 2)
    - Board of Supervisors Social Service Program (Box 2)
    - Bond Issue (1966) (Box 2)
    - Brochures-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Building Authority (Box 2)
    - Building and Safety Department (Box 2)
    - Carport-Maynard and William (Box 2)
    - Central Business District High Rise and Parking Ordinance (Box 2)
    - Central Services (Box 2)
    - Charter Amendment Committee (Box 2)
    - City Clerk (Box 2)
    - City-Township Relations (Box 2)
    - Civic Art Committee (Box 2)
    - Civic Functions, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Civil Defense (Box 3)
    - Civil Rights Commission (Box 3)
    - Civil Rights Coordinating Council (Box 3)
    - Clean Up-Paint Up-Fix Up Committee (Box 3)
    - Code Coordinator (Complaints) (Box 3)
    - Community Antenna Television (Box 3)
    - Community College (Box 3)
    - Conference on Natural Beauty 1966 (Box 3)
    - Conference on Natural Beauty 1967 (Box 3)
    - Conference on Religion and Race (Box 3)
    - Council (Box 3)
    - Council Chaplains (Box 3)
    - Council of Churches (Box 3)
    - Dar Es Salaam delegation visit (Box 3)
    - Dean Promenade (Box 3)
    - Economic Development and Manpower Commission (Box 3)
    - Economic Opportunity Act (Box 3)
    - Efficiency Study Committee, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Efficiency Study Committee (Financing Material) (Box 3)
    - Elm Spray Program (Box 3)
    - Fair Housing Ordinance (Box 3)
    - Fire Department (Box 3)
    - Florida-Farm City Week (Box 3)
    - Forest Avenue Relocation (Box 3)
    - Fourth and Washington Carport (Box 3)
    - French Dukes (drill team) (Box 3)
    - Fuller-Geddes Parkway (Box 3)
    - Gay Jay Nursery School (Box 3)
    - Goals Committee (Box 3)
    - Goals Conference (Box 3)
    - Governor's Conferences (Box 3)
    - Great Lakes Project (Box 3)
    - Health Department (Box 3)
    - Hillside Terrace (Box 3)
    - Housing (Box 4)
    - Housing Commission, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Housing Conference (Box 4)
    - Human Relations Commission, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority (Box 4)
    - Huron Parkway (Box 4)
    - Huron River Watershed Council (Box 4)
    - International Center (Box 4)
    - Israel-Arab Relief (Box 4)
    - Job Corps (Box 4)
    - Job Opportunities (Box 4)
    - Junior Achievement (Box 4)
    - Junior Councilmen (Box 4)
    - Juvenile Jury (Box 4)
    - Kiwanis Club (Box 4)
    - Law Enforcement Conference 1967 (Box 4)
    - League of Women Voters (Box 4)
    - Legal Aid Society (Box 4)
    - Liquor Commission (Box 4)
    - Low Cost Housing (Box 4)
    - Market Commission (Box 4)
    - Mayor's Meetings (Box 4)
    - Mayor's Prayer Breakfast (Box 4)
    - Medicare Alert (Box 4)
    - Metropolitan Fund (Box 4)
    - Metropolitan Fund, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Michigan Conference of Mayors (Box 5)
    - Michigan Legislature (Box 5)
    - Michigan Municipal League (Box 5)
    - Michigan Municipal League Convention 1966 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Municipal League Convention 1967 (Box 5)
    - Michigan State Council for the Arts (Box 5)
    - Michigan United Conservation Clubs (Box 5)
    - Michigan Week 1965 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Week 1966 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Week 1967 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Week 1968 (Box 5)
    - Mill Creek Impoundment (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Letters, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Model Cities (Box 6)
    - Motorcycles (Box 6)
    - National League of Cities, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Natural Resources Committee (Box 6)
    - North Central Ave. (Box 6)
    - Northbelt (Box 6)
    - Notices (Box 6)
    - Optimist Club (Box 6)
    - Parking (Box 6)
    - Parks and Recreation Department (Box 6)
    - People to People Program, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - People to People Program (Box 7)
    - Perry Nursery School (Box 7)
    - Personnel (Box 7)
    - Peru (Box 7)
    - Pittsfield Township (Box 7)
    - Planning Commission (Box 7)
    - Police-Community Relations Committee (Box 7)
    - Police Department, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Poor Peoples Support Committee (Box 7)
    - Proclamations (Box 7)
    - Proclamations, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Project Head Start (Box 8)
    - Project 74 (Box 8)
    - Project Transition (Box 8)
    - Public Relations Ideas (Box 8)
    - Public Works Department (Box 8)
    - Radio Releases (Box 8)
    - Recreation Advisory Board (Box 8)
    - Red Cross (Box 8)
    - Report on Citizens Choice and Control (Box 8)
    - Report-Year End 1966 (Box 8)
    - Report-Year End 1967 (Box 8)
    - Report-Year End 1968 (Box 8)
    - Reports-Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Resolutions of Appreciation (Box 8)
    - Resumé Forms (Box 8)
    - Retirement System (Box 8)
    - Rockefeller, Nelson (Presidential Campaign) (Box 8)
    - Saturday Appointments (Box 8)
    - Selective Service Board (Box 8)
    - Senior Citizens (Box 8)
    - Sesquicentennial of the University 1967, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Sign Ordinance (Box 9)
    - South University Businessmen's Association (Box 9)
    - Southeast Michigan Council of Governments (S.E.M.C.O.G.) (Box 9)
    - Speech-Material (Box 9)
    - State of Michigan (Box 9)
    - Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (Box 9)
    - Talks (Thought Starters) (Box 9)
    - Taxicab Board (Box 9)
    - Time Airlines (Box 9)
    - Togo, Africa, (Dr. Nathaniels) (Box 9)
    - Traffic and Safety Department (Box 9)
    - Transportation, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Transportation Authority (Box 9)
    - Travel Agencies (Box 9)
    - Treasurer (Box 9)
    - Underground Utilities (Box 9)
    - Unions (Box 9)
    - United Fund (Box 9)
    - United Nations (Box 9)
    - U.S. Conference of Mayors (Box 9)
    - U.S. Conference of Mayors- 1966 Convention (Box 9)
    - U.S. Conference of Mayors- 1967 Convention, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - U.S. Conference of Mayors- 1968 Convention (Box 9)
    - U.S. House of Representatives (Box 9)
    - U.S. Senate (Box 9)
    - University-City Relations, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - University Microfilms (Box 9)
    - University of Michigan (Box 9)
    - University of Michigan (Box 10)
    - University of Michigan-Extension Service (Box 10)
    - University of Michigan-Orientation Program (Box 10)
    - University of Michigan-World's Fair (Box 10)
    - University Record (Box 10)
    - Urban Coalition (Box 10)
    - Urban Renewal (Box 10)
    - Utilities Department (Box 10)
    - Veda, Inc. (Box 10)
    - Veteran's Day (Box 10)
    - Vietnam Committee (Box 10)
    - Washtenaw County Planning Commission (Box 10)
    - Washtenaw County Road Commission (Box 10)
    - Welcome Wagon (Box 10)
    - Welfare Department (Box 10)
    - WOIA (Box 10)
    - Wolverine Girls' State (Box 10)
    - Workable Program, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - YM-YWCA (Box 10)
    - Youth Commission (Box 10)
    - Youth Employment Program (Box 10)
    - Youth In Government Day 1965 (Box 10)
    - Zoning Board of Appeals (Box 10)
    - Zwerdling, Isias (90th Birthday) (Box 10)
  - City Council Minutes, Reports and Correspondence
    - April-August, 1965 (Box 10)
    - September 1965-January 1966 (Box 11)
    - February-July 1966 (Box 12)
    - August-December 1966 (Box 13)
    - January-May 1967 (Box 14)
    - June-October 1967 (Box 15)
    - November 1967-March 1968 (Box 16)
    - April-July 1968 (Box 17)
    - August-December 1968 (Box 18)
    - January-April 1969 (Box 19)
  - Other materials
    - Appointments to Boards and Commissions (Box 20)
    - Mayoral Campaign File 1965 (Box 20)
    - Mayoral Campaign File 1967 (Box 21)
    - City Budgets 1964/1965-1966/1967 (Box 21)
    - City Budgets 1967/1968-1968/1969 (Box 22)
    - Michigan Municipal League 1968-1969 (Box 22)
    - Committee of One Hundred (Southeast Michigan local government leaders) 1965-1966 (Box 22)
    - Housing Commission. Referendum 1965 (Box 22)
    - Sign Ordinance 1966 (Box 22)
    - European Trip 1966 (Box 22)
    - Vice President's Conference for Mayors 1965 (Box 23)
    - Christmas Letters 1965-1968 (Box 23)
    - Boy Scouts 1969 (Box 23)
    - Governor George Romney Visit 1968 (Box 23)
    - President Richard Nixon Inaugural 1969 (Box 23)
    - Bermuda Trip 1968 (Box 23)
    - Governor's Special Commission on Urban Problems 1967 (Box 23)
    - Honorary Awards (Box 23)
    - Urban Coalition 1968-1969 (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous Reports (Box 23)
    - Redirection of State Resources 1968-1969 (Box 23)
    - U.S. Conference of Mayors 1968 (Box 24)
    - National League of Cities 1968 (Box 24)
    - Urban Crises Conference 1968 (Box 24)
    - Water Resources 1968 (Box 24)
    - Draft of 1968 Annual Report (Box 24)
    - Blue Ribbon Committee on Financing City Services 1968 (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous Mayoral Papers (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous Mayoral papers (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous published reports (Box 26)
    - Notebooks 1965-1969 concerning local Republican Party affairs, 1 file packet; 1 volume (Box 34)
    - Ann Arbor Register of guests to the city (Box 34)
    - Papers 1967 concerning testimony before U.S. Subcommittee on Fiscal Policy (Box 34)
    - Ann Arbor miscellanea (Box 34)
    - Mayoral miscellanea (Box 34)
    - Personal and biographical (Box 34)
    - Neighborhood Business Revitalization Office, Small Business Administration (Box 34)
    - Photographs (Box 34)
      (see also oversize folder)
- Ann Arbor City Councilman's file
  - City Council file 1960-1964 (Box 27)
  - Campaigns 1960, 1962 (Box 27)
  - Scrapbooks 1959-1960 concerning city elections and council activities (Box 27)
  - Fair Housing Ordinance and Human Relations Commission 1960-1963 (Box 28)
  - New Zoning Law 1961-1963 (Box 29)
  - City Budget 1963-1964 (Box 29)
  - Municipal Airport 1962-1963 (Box 29)
  - Sewage Disposal 1961-1962 (Box 29)
  - Water Supply Facilities 1962 (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous papers and newspaper clippings (Box 29)
- Post-Mayoralty papers and miscellaneous
  - Office of Intergovernmental Relations file 1969-1971 (Box 30)
  - Office of Intergovernmental Relations file 1969-1971 (Box 31)
    (continued)
  - Office of Intergovernmental Relations file 1969-1971 (Box 32)
  - Office of Intergovernmental Relations file 1969-1971 (Box 33)
  - Office of Intergovernmental Relations file 1969-1971 (Box 34)
  - ICC Rail Service Planning Office (Box 35)
  - New Federalism (Box 35)
  - Federalism Seventy-Six, Inc. (Box 35)
  - Florida Southern College (Box 35)
  - Notes concerning Cabinet meeting 1969 (Box 35)
  - Published articles by WEH (Box 35)